Okay, moving along, the next section is the cervix.
Remember that the cervix is the neck,
hence the term cervix, of the uterus,
and it's divided into the exocervix and the endocervix.
Now the idea here is that when you do a clinical exam,
you can actually visualize the exocervix,
and sometimes you can visualize the endocervix.
What's important histologically is that
when you look at the exo and endocervix,
there's a very distinct demarcation between them,
and there are differing types of epithelium
that cover them.
For example, if this is a basement membrane
and we're drawing the exocervix and the endocervix,
then remember that the exocervix,
let's say that's here,
the exocervix is lined by squamous epithelium,
all right, like that.
And so this would be the exocervix.
And then the endocervix is lined by columnar epithelium.
And the distinction between the exo and the endocervix
is so sharp that it's actually a single cell
that you can actually sort of make that distinction between.
It's very, very clear on histology,
and that lends to a very clear demarcation clinically as well.
Here's a picture just highlighting that.
I just want to show you how sharp this demarcation is.
This is the squamous epithelium here,
and you can see this basket weaving of keratin
that's occurring as we get to the top of the epithelium.
And so this is the exocervix here.
And then you can clearly see that here,
you've got all these individual columnar cells,
and so this represents the endocervix.
Now, important to note that this region here
that I'm drawing the arrow towards,
where that demarcation occurs,
that's called the transformation zone.
And the whole story of what we're going to discuss in the cervix
is its story of what happens at the transformation zone.
The only real pathology that we're going to discuss in this section,
sort of the highest yield,
and really the most important clinically as well,
is HPV infection.
Now, remember in our discussion of the vulva
that I told you a lot about HPV.
So HPV is characterized by coelocytic change.
HPV is a DNA virus.
You can subtype that DNA virus using DNA sequencing
into high-risk and low-risk.
Low-risk, for example, 6 and 11,
classically causes a condyloma.
High-risk, for example, 16, 18,
and then 31, 33, and some others,
would result in dysplasia.
And then dysplasia would eventually result in carcinoma.
And so that's the basics that you really have to have
well embedded in your mind concerning HPV.
And that's what I basically stated here.
It's a sexually transmitted DNA virus.
It infects the lower genital tract.
For example, if it infects the vulva,
you get condyloma or dysplasia.
If it infects the vaginal canal,
you can get condyloma or dysplasia.
And if it affects the cervix,
you get condyloma or dysplasia.
And one of the most common regions
within the entire lower genital tract
would be the cervix,
especially the transformation zone.
And that's important.
The transformation zone is the key place
in the lower genital tract where HPV likes to infect.
Now, what's another important interesting thing about HPV
is that when we get an HPV infection,
if someone were to get an HPV infection,
the vast majority of HPV infection
is actually cleared by the immune system.
Probably about 90% of the time
when anyone gets an HPV infection,
that's just gonna be cleared by the immune system.
It's only when persistent infection occurs,
which is relatively rare considering the number
of infections out there.
When persistent infection occurs,
then a risk results for CIN.
And so, again, you need persistent infection.
Now, I've already mentioned,
and I'm just going to repeat here,
that the risk of CIN with persistent infection
depends on the type of HPV.
So, for example, high risks are underlined here
and low risks are underlined here.
And I've already discussed this,
and it's already written in your book as well.
What is very high yield, and I cannot emphasize this enough,
and students need to be able to take this discussion
one step further to this point,
and that is, what makes high risk HPV high risk?
What is it about the virus that actually makes it high risk?
And the answer is that high risk HPVs,
they produce two proteins, E6 and E7.
And what do E6 and E7 do?
They knock out P53 and retinoblastoma respectively.
So, when you have E6 being produced by the HPV virus,
and the high risk HPV virus, that then results
in the destruction of P53.
And you're well aware of the fact that P53
is an important tumor suppressor gene.
Remember that P53, its job is to regulate the G1 to S phase
in the cell cycle.
And it basically looks at the amount of DNA damage
that's present in the cell and makes sure
that the DNA damage is repaired
before the cell goes to S phase.
Remember that if there's too much DNA damage,
P53 has the ability to induce apoptosis.
So, basically, P53 looks at the cell and says,
put your hands up, let me check your DNA.
If the DNA has damage, it blows a molecular whistle
and calls in repair enzymes.
The repair enzymes then fix that DNA
and the cell is allowed to go to S phase.
If there's too much damage, P53 blows a molecular whistle,
calls in a molecule called, do you remember the name?
Bax.
Bax knocks out another molecule, which is BCL2.
Remember that BCL2 is the molecule
that stabilizes the mitochondrial membrane.
So, that loss of stability of the mitochondrial membrane
allows cytochrome C to leak out.
Cytochrome C activates apoptosis and then kills that cell.
So, that's the way by which P53 regulates that G1 to S phase.
And, of course, if you destroy P53,
there's going to be no regulation to remove DNA mutations
or cells that are mutated with their,
or cells in which the DNA is actually mutated.
And so, therefore, loss of P53 would have a major effect on carcinogenesis.
And that's why high-risk HPV can result in dysplasia and then cancer.
And E7, what it does is it knocks out retinoblastoma.
And you recall that retinoblastoma holds a very important molecule,
which is called E2F.
And E2F is necessary for progression to the cell cycle.
You must phosphorylate retinoblastoma before it will release E2F.
If you destroy retinoblastoma, E2F is floating around free
and therefore will be able to be taken up by the cell and moved,
or used by the cell to move into the G1S phase.
So, you need these two essential tumor suppressor genes.
And the high-risk HPVs, they knock out both of these key genes.
This is a very high-yield discussion for examinations.
I cannot emphasize this enough.
It shows up all the time.
All right, now, if a patient were to get persistent high-risk HPV,
the risk would be development of CIN.
And basically, CIN is dysplasia, bad growth,
so that you get atypical cells with high NC ratio,
increased mitotic activity, nuclear atypia,
and choilocytic change because there's an HPV infection.
And these cells begin to pile up in the epithelium of the cervix.
And based on the extent of these dysplastic cells,
we can divide CIN into multiple subtypes.
So, let's do that here.
This is the cervix, okay?
And let's pretend that the cervix is made up of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 cells,
just as an example.
If the dysplasia involves any one of these first three cells,
that would be the first one-third, we would call that CIN 1.
If the dysplasia progresses and extends beyond that to involve any cells within this middle two-thirds,
to now the first six cells in that layer, for example, we call that CIN 2.
If the dysplasia extends up to involve most of that epithelium,
then we call that CIN 3.
And if the dysplasia involves the entire thickness of the epithelium,
we call that carcinoma in situ.
Okay, key important question.
What's the distinction between dysplasia and carcinoma?
Why do we make that distinction?
Can you remember from the neoplasia lectures,
what's the key feature that distinguishes dysplasia from carcinoma?
The answer is reversibility.
CIN 1 has the potential to reverse.
CIN 2 has the potential to reverse.
And CIN 3 very, very rarely could potentially reverse.
But once you have carcinoma in situ, there is no reversibility.
And carcinoma in situ, the next step will be invasion,
producing a squamous cell carcinoma, an invasive squamous cell carcinoma.
Now remember that CIN 1, it reverses about 66% of the time.
And CIN 2 reverses about 33% of the time.
But CIN 3 is very unlikely to reverse.
So the more you progress in CIN, the less likely you are to reverse back to something
less than the level at which you're at.
So that's an important understanding that should be in our minds concerning CIN.
And that is that we can divide, that is that we can subclassify the extent of dysplasia.
Now here's a classic picture of CIN.
And let me take you back a couple pictures and just show you the normal for a minute.
So here was the normal, and I'm going to erase that to just show you that this is what the normal
squamous epithelium looks like.
Notice that the cells become pink as you go towards the top.
They become smaller, and their nucleus becomes smaller.
Look at how tiny that nucleus is, for example, compared to the nucleus there.
Now if we go back and look at the picture that I just showed you, look at these cells.
They're not becoming pink.
They're really dark blue.
Whatever's at the bottom looks exactly like what's at the top.
So from top to bottom here, we've got dysplastic cells.
Now basically, if I were to look here, I would say that this is carcinoma in situ,
at this point here.
Maybe if I were to look here, and I see a little bit of pinking of the cells,
and a little bit of maturation, I might call that area CIN 3, just to highlight this notion.
But the point is, when you look at an area like this, you've got these large blue cells
from top to bottom.
You're really going to call this carcinoma in situ.
So that's what I want to highlight from this image present in your text.
Now again, you know that CIN progresses stepwise, so that you go from 1 to 2,
then 2 to 3, 3 to CIS, and eventually to invasive carcinoma.
But it's not inevitable.
As I told you, it may regress.
In particular, CIN 1 regresses 66% of the time.
CIN 2 regresses about 33% of the time, and CIN 3 is very unlikely to regress,
but is very likely to progress to carcinoma in situ.
Now of course, once patients get carcinoma in situ, they'll eventually develop invasive carcinoma,
and then we'd call that cervical carcinoma.
Now the invasive carcinoma, the key feature is that it goes through the basement membrane.
That's what distinguishes carcinoma in situ from invasive carcinoma.
The invasive carcinoma usually arises in these patients
in a middle-aged woman.
And the idea here is that the HPV infection will occur early in the woman's life,
like the age of 20 or 25.
And it takes about 25 to 30 years before the patient actually develops a full-blown carcinoma.
And that's because it takes time to go through this dysplasia carcinoma sequence.
The classic presentation would be vaginal bleeding.
The woman would present with either bleeding from the vaginal canal or post-coital bleeding,
bleeding after intercourse.
Those are two classic presentations for cervical carcinoma.
What's the key risk factor for cervical carcinoma?
We've already discussed it.
It's high-risk HPV infection.
Now everybody knows that.
You need to know again that the high-risk viruses are 16 and 18,
and then 31 and 33 are also common.
There are other ones.
They are a little less common.
You need to know that the high-risk HPV produces E6 and E7.
E6 knocks out P53.
E7 knocks out retinoblastoma.
So that's what I would say concerning the key risk factors.
Now there are some secondary risk factors that will also increase the risk.
And there's two that you really should be aware of.
The first is smoking.
Now it's important to remember smoking here.
Generally speaking, when I think about smoking, I think about the things that make sense.
For example, obviously smoking is going to increase the risk of oropharyngeal carcinoma
because the smoke hits the oropharynx.
Obviously smoking would increase the risk of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma
because the smoke hits the esophagus.
Some of it goes down the throat when the patient's breathing in, for example.
Obviously smoking would increase the risk of lung cancer
because it goes to the lung.
It makes sense.
The smoking would increase the risk of kidney cancer and urothelial carcinoma
because the kidney takes all of those carcinogens that go into the blood
and it concentrates it in the urine.
And so anything that the urine is going to touch
is going to have an increased risk of cancer when a patient smokes.
So those all make sense.
But there's two that you kind of have to remember beyond those that make sense.
One is cervix and the other is pancreas.
So an important risk factor for cervical carcinoma is smoking.
An important risk factor for pancreatic carcinoma is smoking.
So that's what I would like to say about smoking.
Now immunodeficiency is very high yield.
Why?
Because remember that it's the vast majority of the time we actually use our immune system
to destroy the virus.
And so the immune system is essential in this disease to remove the essential cause,
the initiator of the disease to begin with.
And so patients who are immune deficient, they have an increased risk of developing cervical carcinoma.
And interestingly, if you were to go and take a list of the AIDS-defining illnesses,
remember that there are a series of illnesses that you can use to call a patient who has HIV as
now having AIDS.
And those are called the AIDS-defining illnesses.
One of them on that list is cervical carcinoma.
So that if a patient actually develops a cervical carcinoma with HIV,
that's a potential AIDS-defining illness.
And this is a very high yield point to be aware of.
Okay, now remember that when patients get cervical carcinoma, they can actually get two types.
So we've got the exocervix and the endocervix.
And you've got squamous cells in the exocervix.
And then you've got columnar cells in the endocervix.
So the patients can develop squamous cell carcinoma.
And they can also develop an adenocarcinoma.
Squamous is much more common.
Adeno is a little bit less rare.
It's a little bit less common.
But what I really want you to remember is that both are associated with HPV.
Patients who get squamous cell carcinoma, it is driven by HPV.
But patients who get adenocarcinoma, it is also driven by HPV.
And examiners like to ask you,
which of the following is due to HPV?
Squamous cell carcinoma, squamous cell and adenocarcinoma, etc.
And so you need to know that adenocarcinoma of the cervix is also driven by HPV.
Another very important principle concerning cervical cancer is that the tumor tends to grow locally
and doesn't metastasize until very, very late.
And so the classic findings are when you have an advanced tumor, one of the classic findings is
hydronephrosis.
Now, the idea here is that the tumor sort of bores through the anterior uterine wall into the bladder.
And when it gets into the bladder, it blocks the ureters.
And it's the blocking of the ureters that results then in hydronephrosis with eventual post renal failure.
And the most common cause, or I should say one of the most common causes of death in patients with cervical cancer,
is post renal failure with hydronephrosis.
So we should be well aware of the fact that the cancers of the cervix, one of the important characteristics
of these cancers is that they tend to locally create symptoms rather than metastasizing to a distant site.
And that's the mechanism by which patients can expire with this cancer, very high yield to be aware of.
Remember that one of the ways by which we can avoid the whole issue of cervical cancer is screening.
And screening is essential, and the goal of screening in the context of cervix is to catch that dysplasia before it becomes cancer.
Remember that I told you that patients normally get infected at about the age of 25 or, you know, 20,
and it takes about 10 to 20 years, in most cases 20 years, before you actually develop that carcinoma.
And so we've got this 20-year window where we can actually catch the patients with dysplasia
and remove that dysplasia before it becomes cancer.
And the way by which we find that dysplasia is called the pap smear.
So the pap smear is the gold standard for screening, and it is the most successful cancer screening test developed to date.
Now the idea here is that you take a brush, you go to the transformation zone,
and you scrape away the cells using that brush, and then you put them on a slide,
and you look at those cells under the microscope.
Under the microscope, we look for dysplasia, and when we see dysplasia, we see characteristic features of malignant cells.
For example, we see cells with dark nuclei and high NC ratios, and this is one of the key screening tests for cervical cancer.
All right, so here's a picture of cytology, and this is a picture of a pap smear.
Basically, this is a normal squamous cell, and these are the malignant cells, and you can clearly see that,
compare the nuclear size, this nucleus is tiny, this nucleus is huge.
This cell has a very low NC ratio with a lot of cytoplasm and a little bit of nucleus.
This cell has a very high NC ratio, a lot of nucleus, a very little bit of cytoplasm.
The nucleus looks dark and hyperchromatic, and so, again, these are all the features that we would expect to see in dysplasia,
and that's important to bear in mind.
Now, when a patient has an abnormal pap smear, remember that the pap smear is a screening test,
and every screening test in medicine must be confirmed, and so the confirmatory test is called colposcopy,
where we basically put in a magnifying glass, introduce a magnifying glass into the vaginal canal and view the cervix,
and when we view the cervix, we can apply acid to the cervix, and we can then detect areas of abnormality and biopsy those,
and so when a patient has an abnormal pap smear, the next step will be biopsy,
and biopsy will then be sent to the pathologist, and the pathologist will then determine the extent of dysplastic cells.
There are some limitations to the pap smear, and examiners like to go after those limitations.
First of all, if a pap smear is performed, but it's not done at the transformation zone,
then the screening would be inadequate, you would not have actually tested the area that you wanted to test,
and so that would result in a false negative test, so that's one limitation of the pap smear.
Another limitation of the pap smear is that it does not detect adenocarcinoma very well.
Now remember that we have a dysplastic sequence where we had CIN1, CIN2, CIN3 carcinoma in situ,
and then invasive squamous cell carcinoma, but that applied to squamous lesions.
And adenocarcinoma, it's much more difficult to detect, and it doesn't go through that same sequence, obviously.
And so there is a limited efficacy in screening for adenocarcinoma.
Now what's interesting is that despite the pap smear, all the great things that we have to say about the pap smear,
that all applies to squamous cell carcinoma.
And despite the pap smear, the incidence of adenocarcinoma has not decreased significantly.
We're highlighting, again, the general principle that the pap smear is good for squamous cell carcinoma
and its precursor lesions, but is not good for adenocarcinoma or its precursor lesions.
The last point that I want to make concerns immunizations.
Remember that, number one, immunization is effective in preventing HPV infection.
That's the current understanding.
The current immunization that we use, or the vaccine, is a quadrivalent vaccine.
It covers four subtypes.
Important to know.
You've got to know these four subtypes.
Six and eleven, they protect against the formation of condyloma.
And sixteen and eighteen protect against the formation of CIN or VAIN or VIN, right?
Dysplasia of the lower genital tract, especially CIN.
Now sixteen and eighteen are high-risk subtypes, and they are the most common high-risk
subtypes involved in that dysplastic carcinoma sequence.
Protection lasts for about five years, so you have to re-immunize every five years.
And remember that the patient still must get pap smears.
Why?
Why do they still need to get pap smears?
The answer is because you're only protecting against sixteen and eighteen.
What about thirty-one, thirty-three, and the other less common subtypes that could also
result in dysplasia?
So we have not eliminated by a vaccine the possibility of dysplasia.
Therefore, patients still must undergo pap smear, and that's the high-yield principle
to be aware of.
So that closes off our section, and we're going to move up the tract next and go to
endometrium and myometrium.